威尔·史密斯：下赢国际象棋你需要什么？
WILL SMITH: What do you need to win a game of chess?
耐心  巧妙的战术  丰富的想象力
Patience, clever tactics, loads of imagination.
你看起来很紧张
You look nervous.
什么使我们成为人类
What makes us human
是我们脑袋里的三镑重的糊状物
is the squishy triple-pounder inside our heads.
“将军”
Check.
它让我们把我们的朋友“将死”
It lets us checkmate our friends,
建造摩天大楼
build skyscrapers,
把我们中的一些人送到太空
and lift a special few of us into space.
八名宇航员  他们在的太空时间超过1000天
Eight astronauts with over 1,000 days in space between them
能告诉我们上面的情况怎么样
can tell us how being up there
帮助他们真正理解下面发生的事情
helped them to truly understand what goes on down here.
杰夫·霍夫曼：从太空中你可以看到全局
JEFF HOFFMAN: From space you get the big picture.
你真的看到了人类文明
You really see human civilization
在你下方展开
spread out below you.
妮可·斯托特：据我们所知
NICOLE STOTT: As far as we know,
宇宙中没有其他生物像我们一样
there's nobody else like us out there in the universe.
杰里·林格：我能理解的唯一原因是
JERRY LINENGER: The only reason I'm able to comprehend
地球不可思议的复杂性
the incredible complexity of the Earth
是因为我的大脑非常复杂
is because I have an incredibly complex brain inside my head.
我们是这个星球上唯一的
We are the only species on this planet
可以在我们的头脑中构建现实
that can construct realities in our mind
然后去建造它的物种
and then go actually build it.
国 家 地 理 倾 情 呈 现
史密斯：但30亿年来
SMITH: But for three billion years,
生物甚至没有大脑
life didn't even have a brain.
梅尔文：关于我们大脑进化的故事
MELVIN: The story of how our mind evolved
在这一块奇怪的石头上
on this one strange rock
是偶然  巧合和不可能的偶然之一
is one of chance, coincidence and impossible odds.
史密斯：我要告诉你最不可思议的地方
SMITH: I am going to tell you about the most incredible place.
奇怪的联系
The weird connections,
创造我们的动力
the dynamic forces that created us.
一个拥有像你和我一样复杂大脑的物种
A species with a brain as complex as yours and mine.
被 点 亮 的 星 球
觉 醒
人脑是独一无二的
The human brain is unique.
不仅因为它的大小  而且因为它的能力
Not just because of its size, but also its ability.
它可以应对危险  苛刻的挑战
It can meet challenges that are dangerous, demanding.
史密斯：而且非常荒谬
SMITH: And wonderfully absurd.
史密斯：在西班牙  每年有数千人聚在一起
SMITH: In Spain, thousands come together every year
用人体建造塔楼
to build towers out of people.
史密斯：一座十层楼高的人塔  上面有最年轻的孩子
SMITH: A ten-story human tower with the youngest kids on top.
是的
Right.
克劳迪娅和玛丽娜  他们七岁
Claudia and Marina, they're seven.
史密斯：人类和地球上其他生物都不一样
SMITH: Humans are like no other creature on Earth.
我们做的这些事情似乎毫无意义
We do these things that might seem pointless,
不是因为我们愚蠢  而是因为我们聪明
not because we're stupid; because we're smart.
我们一起工作
And we work as one.
是那种把我们的思想联系在一起的能力
It's that ability to link our minds together
把那些女孩放在塔顶上
that put those girls on top of that tower
把男人和女人放在太空中
and also put men and women up in space.
其中之一是莱兰·梅尔文
One of them is Leland Melvin.
前NFL球员  机械工程师和宇航员
Former NFL player, mechanical engineer, and astronaut.
坚强  聪明  勇敢
Strong, smart, brave,
而且几乎势不可挡
and pretty much unstoppable.
但利兰几乎没有飞到太空
But Leland nearly didn't make it to space.
训练中的一次意外使他的梦想停止了
An accident in his training brought his dreams to a halt.
梅尔文：真正模拟地球太空行走的唯一方法
MELVIN: The only way to really simulate a spacewalk on Earth
在游泳池里
is in a pool.
我记得我穿上宇航服  戴上手套  穿上靴子
I remember getting in the suit, putting my gloves on, my boots.
梅尔文：当你穿着宇航服下潜的时候
MELVIN: As you're going down in the spacesuit,
你得清理耳朵
you have to clear your ears.
梅尔文：往下潜到十英尺
MELVIN: Ten feet down,
我意识到泡沫塑料块
I realized that the Styrofoam block,
堵住鼻子吹气来清空耳朵
you press your nose against it to clear your ears,
我的头盔不见了
was missing in my helmet.
我告诉测试主管  把耳机的音量调大
I tell the test director, turn the volume in the headset up.
我努力使压力均衡
I was straining to equalize the pressure.
然后  我立即听到除了静电以外什么都没有
And then, I immediately hear nothing but static.
他们把我从水里拖出来
They were pulling me out of the water.
当时我看到飞行外科医生朝我走来
And now I see the flight surgeon walking towards me.
他伸手摸我的右耳
He reaches up and touches my right ear.
他在动嘴唇  但我什么也没听到
He's moving his lips, but I don't hear anything he's saying.
然后我能感觉到血开始往下滴
And then I can feel the blood starting to trickle down
在我脸的侧面
on the side of my face.
我想  哇！ 真的出了点问题
I'm like, 'Wow, something's really wrong.'
我完全聋了
I was completely deaf.
我的大脑和耳朵之间的联系
Somehow the connection between my brain and my ears
被切断了
had been severed,
以及我去太空的机会
along with my chances of going to space.
这次事故使我深表感激
The accident gave me a profound appreciation
在我们认为理所当然的事情上
in what we take for granted.
使我们成为我们的东西：我们的大脑
The thing that makes us us: our brain.
人脑使我们与
The human brain sets us apart
地球上所有其他生物都不同
from all other creatures on this planet.
它看起来像一块果冻
It might look like a lump of Jell-O,
但它是我们宇宙中最复杂的东西
but it's the most complex thing in our universe.
内部有一个拥有100万亿连接的庞大网络
Inside, there's a vast network with 100 trillion connections.
这比我们银河系中的恒星数量还要多
That's more than the number of stars in our own Milky Way.
它承载着我们的记忆
It hosts our memories.
我们的感觉
Our sensations.
我们的梦想
Our dreams.
所有这些都依赖于发射电信号的细胞
And all this depends on tiny cells firing electrical signals.
其中有860亿
There's 86 billion of them.
我们称之为神经元
We call them neurons.
史密斯：860亿
SMITH: 86 billion.
真的
Wow.
我很高兴有人在数
I'm just glad someone else was counting.
但问题是：
But here's the thing:
地球上的大多数生命在没有大脑的情况下都很好
most of life on Earth does just fine without a brain.
我说的是地球上一些最古老的居民
I'm talking about some of Earth's oldest inhabitants.
有些无脑生物是如此成功
Some brainless creatures are so successful,
你甚至可以在太空中看到它们
you can even see them from space.
林格：在阳光明媚的日子
LINENGER: On a bright, sunny day,
我往下看了1000英里
I'm looking down, and for 1,000 miles,
我看到一个有组织的珊瑚城
I see an organized city of coral.
佩吉·惠特森：它们只是发光
PEGGY WHITSON: They just glow.
就像世界上最美的艺术一样
It's just like the most beautiful art in the world.
梅尔文：这一抹色彩
MELVIN: This burst of color.
我从未见过如此鲜艳的色彩
I'd never seen colors that vibrant before.
令人惊讶的是  珊瑚是巨大的  静止的结构
It's kind of amazing that corals are vast, motionless structures,
没有大脑就可以茁壮成长
that thrive without a brain.
史密斯：在这个无脑的国家
SMITH: In the country of the brainless,
小小脑袋就是国王
the tiny-brained is king.
见见这个小家伙
Meet this little guy.
他和我们的共同点比你想象的要多
He's got more in common with us than you might think.
在里面  他也有神经元  只是数量不多
Inside, he's got neurons, too, just not as many.
大约200
About 200.
有点像入门包
Kind of a starter kit.
他是一个寻找家的婴儿海鞘
He's a baby sea squirt looking for a home.
他的神经元做简单的事情
His neurons do simple stuff,
就像探测光线和抽动尾巴一样
like detect light and twitch his tail.
但问题是：
But here's the thing:
一旦找到合适的石头  他的游泳日就结束了
once he's found the right rock, his swimming days are over.
在他的余生里  他一直呆在原地
For the rest of his life, he stays put.
他甩下尾巴  消化使它移动的神经元
He dumps the tail and consumes the neurons that made it move.
然后  它成长为一个巨大的  古老的海鞘
Then, it grows into a big, old sea squirt.
将  使用或丢失  提升到一个全新的水平
Takes 'use it or lose it' to a whole new level.
梅尔文：你知道  这是一种奇怪的想法
MELVIN: It's kind of a freaky thought that, you know,
当神经元发育时  它们不是用来思考的
when neurons were developed, they weren't for thinking.
它们是为了简单的运动
They were for simple motion or movement.
但是有一天  像这样的神经元  我们大脑中的神经元
But one day, neurons like those, the ones inside our brains,
有助于创造事物
would help create things
就像火箭飞船进入太空一样
like rocket ships going to space,
城市和音乐
cities and music.
史密斯：抽动尾巴移动一两码
SMITH: Making a tail twitch to move a yard or two
只需要几个神经元
requires just a few neurons.
但是  更先进的东西
However, the more advanced stuff,
这需要更多的东西
that needs an awful lot more.
生物需要感知周围的环境
Life needs to sense its surroundings,
否则  它只是在黑暗中挣扎
otherwise, it's just flailing around in the dark.
史密斯：没有什么比人脑更复杂的了
SMITH: There is nothing more complex than the human brain.
但更复杂的是
But the more complicated something is,
越是可能出错
the more ways it can go wrong.
（鸟叫声）
(bird shrieks)
梅尔文：在我的训练事故之后
MELVIN: After my training accident,
医生们不知道我出了什么问题
the doctors couldn't figure out what was wrong with me.
一切看起来都完好无损
Everything looked physically intact,
但他们不能治好我
but they couldn't fix me.
我完全聋了
I was completely deaf.
我进入太空的目标似乎被挫败了
My goal of getting to space seemed to be thwarted.
但我能想到的只是
But all I could think about
我是否曾听过我再次演奏的音乐
was whether I'd ever hear music that I played again.
音乐一直是我生物的重要组成部分
Music has been such a big part of my life.
（弹钢琴）
(playing piano)
所以  当音乐安静的时候…
And so, when the music was silent...
就在那时  我崩溃了  开始哭泣
That's when I just broke down and started crying.
史密斯：利兰的耳朵很好
SMITH: Leland's ears were fine.
这不是问题所在
That's not where the problem was.
因为你不只是用耳朵听
Because you don't just hear with your ears,
你的大脑也能听到
you also hear with your brain.
所有感官都一样
It's the same for all the senses,
他们把我们的大脑与外界联系起来
they link our brains to the outside world.
数百代人的进化都是为了适应这个世界
And over hundreds of generations they evolve to suit that world,
不管有多严厉
no matter how harsh it is.
史密斯：猎人在这里已经住了几千年了
SMITH: Hunters have lived here for thousands of years.
但为了生存  他们借用了生物的感官
But to survive, they borrow the senses of a creature
在这里呆得更久了
that's been here even longer.
史密斯：老鹰就像一个武器望远镜
SMITH: The eagle is like a weaponized telescope.
它能看见两英里外的狐狸
It can see a fox up to two miles away.
在这里  这是为生存而战的关键工具
Out here, that's a crucial tool in the fight for survival.
史密斯：但是像鹰一样看东西
SMITH: But to see like an eagle,
你需要的不仅仅是鹰眼
you need more than eagle eyes;
你需要一个鹰脑
you need an eagle brain.
梅尔文：眼睛传递着我们周围世界的大量数据
MELVIN: Eyes deliver masses of data about the world around us,
以及所有拯救生命的数据
and all that lifesaving data
需要一些强有力的东西来理解它
needed something powerful to make sense of it.
简单地说  如果你是有眼睛的动物
Simply put, if you're an animal with eyes,
你需要比海鞘更大的大脑
you're gonna need a bigger brain than a sea squirt.
眼睛是真正的游戏改变者
Eyes were a real game changer.
但不仅仅是眼睛
But it's not just the eyes.
生物必须发展出一系列的感官
Creatures had to develop an array of senses
每一个都经过校准处理
that are each calibrated to deal
随着地球环境的不断变化
with the ever-changing environment of Planet Earth.
不仅仅是不新鲜的甜点
Not just barren desserts,
但是这些茂密的丛林
but these very dense jungles,
丰富的海洋礁
teeming ocean reefs,
甚至是冰冷的北极垃圾
and even icy Arctic waste.
地球上各种各样的景观发挥了重要作用
The planet's varied landscapes played a significant role
动物的感觉
in how animals sense.
史密斯：他们怎么办  我们怎么办
SMITH: What goes for them, goes for us.
这颗行星也塑造了我们的感官
The planet shaped our senses, too.
你可能没注意到
It's something you might not notice
除非你离开这个星球
unless you leave the planet.
麦克·马西米诺：我们的感官已经进化了
MIKE MASSIMINO: Our senses have evolved
来适应地球
to operate on Planet Earth.
梅杰米森：当你在太空时
MAE JEMISON: When you're up in space,
内耳没有上下运动
the inner ear isn't registering an up and down.
梅尔文：所以  你的方向感
MELVIN: So, your sense of orientation
只来自你的眼睛
only comes from your eyes.
马西米诺：你知道那种奇怪的感觉
MASSIMINO: You know that weird feeling
在你的胃深处
in the pit of your stomach,
好像你越过过山车的顶部时
when you go over the top of a rollercoaster?
基本上在那种感觉持续了一整天
I was basically in that moment for an entire day.
斯托特：我们是地球人
STOTT: We're Earthlings.
我们就是这样
That's just who we are.
梅尔文：原始大脑感官的进化
MELVIN: The evolution of the senses in the primitive brain
允许生物与我们的星球互动
have allowed living creatures to interact with our planet
以前所未有的方式
in a way like never before.
但是从太空看我们的星球
But looking at our planet from space,
你可以看到它不仅仅是变化的  它是动态的
you can see it's not just varied, it's dynamic.
史密斯：有时候  环境变化很快
SMITH: Sometimes, the environment changes quickly,
当这种情况发生时  你必须尽快适应
and when that happens, you have to be just as fast to adapt.
就像海平面毫无预警地上升
Like when the sea level rises without warning,
现在  你是一个孤岛的弃儿
and now, you're an island castaway.
猕猴的手非常棒
Macaques are great with their hands.
他们剥水果  爬树  做彼此的头发
They peel fruit, climb trees, and do each other's hair.
但在这些岛屿上  它们所做的事情是其他猕猴所不具备的
But on these islands, they do something no other macaques do.
他们用石头作为剥牡蛎壳的工具
They use rocks as tools to shuck oysters.
猕猴通常不吃它们
Macaques don't normally eat them,
但当他们被上涨的海水搁浅时
but when they were stranded by the rising sea,
他们需要新的吃饭方式
they needed new ways to get a meal.
他们不是天生就具备这种技能的
They weren't born with this skill;
一只聪明的猴子必须解决这个问题
a smart monkey had to work it out.
这是只有复杂的大脑才能做到的  --
This is something only complex brains can do--
不仅仅是感觉和反应
not just sense and react,
但学习
but learn,
适应并解决问题
adapt and problem solve.
但仅仅因为猕猴能学会剥牡蛎皮
But just because a macaque can learn to shuck oysters
并不意味着它会开一家海鲜餐馆
doesn't mean it's gonna open a seafood restaurant.
只有人类才能做出这种精神上的飞跃
Only a human would make that mental leap.
那么  我们为什么会如此不同呢
So, how come we're so different?
史密斯：猴子是太空中第一批灵长类动物
SMITH: Monkeys were the first primates in space,
但这不是他们的主意
but it wasn't exactly their idea.
事实上  他们可能反对
In fact, they were probably against it.
那么  为什么我们是有着伟大想法的猿类
So, how come we're the apes with the big ideas?
好吧  说来话长
Well, it's a long story.
关于可能不存在的事物的故事
A story about something that may not exist
太阳系的其他地方
anywhere else in the solar system,
也许是宇宙
maybe the universe.
火
Fire.
我是酋长夫人
负责管理圣火
这个火是我们和先祖的直接纽带
如果火熄灭了
我们和先祖就会永远失去联系
史密斯：希姆巴人一直在燃烧着同一团火
SMITH: The Himba people have kept this same fire burning
世世代代
for generations.
我们拿柴灰来编辫子
有了火
我们可以加热石头和植物
制造烟雾用来熏香
火是我们生存的必需品
史密斯：据我们所知  这颗行星是唯一的
SMITH: As far as we know, this planet is the only one
有适当的燃烧条件
with the right conditions for fire to burn.
但有一件事是火给了我们最重要的
But there's one thing that fire gives us above all else.
我们吃的所有东西都是用火烹饪
我们把肉放入大火中
我们才能很好地烹制
食物才好吃
史密斯：但是烹调食物有好处
SMITH: But cooking food does something
这比让它可口更重要
that's way more important than just making it tasty.
梅尔文：哇  我们有火了  准备好吃饭了吗
MELVIN: Woo! We got fire, are we ready for food?
作为人类  我们有着这些渴望力量的大脑
We as humans have these power-hungry brains.
我们身体的一大块能量
A big chunk of our body's energy
必须用来让它们保持运转
has to be used to keep them running.
来 宝贝  翻个身
Turn, baby, turn.
通过烹饪  我们实际上正在
By cooking, we're actually breaking down
破坏食物的细胞壁
the cell walls of the food
因而释放出更多的营养和卡路里
that releases so many more nutrients and calories,
为我们的大脑加满油
to help fuel our big brains.
我们物种历史上的一个关键时刻
One of the key moments in the history of our species
是我们的祖先用火的时候
was when our ancestors harnessed fire.
好吧  把盘子拿来
Alright, get your plates.
理论认为  烹饪让我们获得更多的能量
The theory goes, cooking let us get more energy
从每一口食物中
out of every bite of food.
所以我们用更少的时间来喂养我们的大脑
So we spent less time feeding our brain
还有更多的时间使用它
and more time using it.
史密斯：试着去一个不受火影响的日子
SMITH: Try going a day that isn't touched by fire.
你无法想象没有它的生物
You couldn't imagine life without it.
但是一个可以控制火焰的大脑
But a brain that could harness fire
可能一开始就没有进化
may not have evolved in the first place
如果不是因为这么强大的力量
if it wasn't for a force so powerful,
它是地球上最高的山脉
it made the highest mountains on Earth.
史密斯：化石告诉我们这些山
SMITH: The fossils tell us that these mountains,
曾经在海底  现金被推到了高空
once at the bottom of the sea, were forced high into the sky.
当你在轨道上时
LINENGER: When you're in orbit,
当你经过喜马拉雅山时
as you come over the Himalaya Mountains,
你几乎觉得你需要启动一点推进器
you almost feel like you need to fire the thrusters a little bit.
你可以知道次大陆在哪里
You can tell where that subcontinent
刚刚挤进亚洲大陆
just jammed into the Asian continent
把那些山推倒
and thrust those mountains up.
克里斯·哈德菲尔德：平滑平坦度之间的碰撞
CHRIS HADFIELD: This collision between the smooth flatness
关于印度和这些崎岖  褶皱的山脉
of India and these rugged, crumpled mountains,
就像看着一辆超慢速的火车残骸
it's like watching a super slow-motion train wreck.
马西米诺：离得越远
MASSIMINO: The further you get away,
你可以看到这些主要的主题
you can kind of see these overarching themes
我们星球的形成方式
to the way our planet is formed.
梅尔文：正是这些力量会改变
MELVIN: It was forces like these that would transform
我们岩石的一个特定角落
one particular corner of our rock
进入人类的摇篮
into the cradle of humanity.
东非大裂谷
The Great Rift Valley in East Africa
曾经是一片郁郁葱葱的绿色森林  是猿类的天堂
was once a lush green forest, a paradise for apes.
但是地壳移动  山脉上升
But the Earth's crust shifted, mountains rose,
气候也发生了变化  使得这里的生物变得更加艰难
and the climate changed, making it a much tougher place to live.
很难确切知道我们的祖先是如何适应的
It's hard to really know exactly how our ancestors adapted
数百万年来
over millions of years.
这些变化可能促使类人猿做事
The changes may have pushed apes to do things
比如创新工具
like innovate the tools.
或者双腿行走
Or walk on two legs.
甚至可以利用火势
And even harness fire.
不管是什么  我们都是早期人类
Whatever it was, we came out the other side as early humans,
有更大的头脑
with bigger brains.
史密斯：我们在地球上实现了飞跃
SMITH: We took off across the planet,
我们带来了一种独特的人类技能
and there was one uniquely human skill we brought with us.
我在这儿  跟你说话
Here I am, talking to you,
你们中的一些人甚至在听
and some of you are even listening.
你听到的可能是最强大的工具
What you're hearing is probably the most powerful tool
我们已经掌握了
we've ever mastered.
那么  你怎么能有一个能讲一个好故事的大脑呢？
So, how do you get a brain that can tell a damn good story?
史密斯：我们说话
SMITH: We speak.
史密斯：我们把符号和声音与思想和事物联系起来
SMITH: We link signs and sounds to thoughts and things,
以无数的方式  创造出几乎无限的意义
in countless ways, creating almost infinite meanings.
这需要很大的脑力
That takes a lot of brain power.
朱莉Masaki：搬到香港真是太神奇了
JULIE MISAKI: Moving to Hong Kong has been amazing.
我来自日本
I'm originally from Japan,
但是我在香港已经住了六年了
but I've lived in Hong Kong for six years now.
但它也有挑战
But it has its challenges.
即使只是买晚餐也会变得复杂
Even just buying dinner can get complicated.
我们很多外国人都想学汉语
A lot of us foreigners try to learn Chinese,
但这并不总是容易的
but it's not always easy.
一个词实际上可以有多种含义
One word can actually have many meanings,
取决于你使用的音调
depending on the tone you use.
比如说  如果我说  肖    意思是  烧
For example, if I say xiao, it means burn,
或者小  意思很小
or xiao, it means little,
或者小笑  意思是笑
or xiao, it means laugh.
用错误的语调  你可能会遇到大麻烦
Use the wrong tone, you could be in big trouble.
梅尔文：只有我们人类
MELVIN: It's only us human beings
已经发展出复杂的语言
that have developed complex language.
与其他语言不同
Unlike many other languages,
中国人使用大脑的音乐区域
Chinese uses the musical areas of the brain
从所有这些音调中提取意义
to extract meaning from all those tones.
这需要很大的处理能力
And that takes a lot of processing power.
但真正重要的问题是
But the really big question is
为什么我们有任何语言
why we have any language at all.
部分原因是我们的大脑很大
It's partly due to the size of our big brains.
但可能还有另一个因素在起作用
But there could be another factor at play.
一种理论是  它是非常微小的东西
One theory is that it was something really tiny.
有一种叫做foxp2的基因
There's a version of a gene, called FOXP2,
只有我们人类拥有
that only us humans have.
把它拿走  你就很难说话了
Take it away, and you'll struggle to talk.
没人知道我们是怎么产生这种变异的
No one knows how we've got this mutation.
但我们知道…
But we do know...
…它给了我们更精确的控制
...it gave us more precise control
通过我们的嘴和舌头肌肉
over our mouth and our tongue muscles.
让我们发出更复杂的声音
And that let us make more sophisticated sounds,
帮助我们把思想变成文字
helping us turn thoughts into words.
史密斯：小的基因突变使我们
SMITH: Small genetic twists turned us
一群咕噜咕噜的人
from a bunch of folks who grunt
对于一个能分辨晓和晓的物种来说
to a species that can tell xiao from xiao,
来自"xiao"
from xiao.
分享想法  交流想法
Sharing ideas, communicating them,
让我们做那些不可能的事情
lets us do things that alone would be impossible.
这是开拓者所熟知的
Something pioneers know full well.
洛基·罗宾逊：好吧  我们开始吧
ROCKY ROBINSON: Okay, let's do it.
我得到了各种——我把它擦掉了
I'm getting all kinds-- I've wiped it off,
但是我身上有各种各样的盐
but I have all kinds of salt on me.
我的盾牌被盐覆盖了
My shield got covered in salt.
男：把水泵关掉
MAN: Turn the water pump off.
罗宾逊：我们在玻利维亚
ROBINSON: We're here in Bolivia
试图打破摩托车世界陆地速度纪录
trying to break the motorcycle world land speed record.
我们可能没有更好的机会
We probably don't have a better opportunity
比我们现在看到的还要快
than we have right now to see just how fast this bike will go.
这是一个巨大的团队努力
This is a huge team effort.
我们交流很多  团队和我
We communicate a lot, the team and I.
沟通是一个巨大的优势
Communication is a huge advantage.
需要这么多人
It takes so many people
制造出这种口径的机器
to come up with a machine of this caliber.
你让这些人为你做这些事
You have all these people doing all this stuff for you,
但一旦顶篷关闭…
but once that canopy closes...
你准备好了吗
MAN: You ready?
罗宾逊：你就靠自己了
ROBINSON: You're all alone.
男：45岁  来吧  洛基
MAN: 45, hit it, Rocky!
无线电广播：全速  333.9
MAN ON RADIO: Full speed, 333.9.
广播员：罗杰  六岁
MAN ON RADIO: Roger, six.
罗宾逊：哇  哇  哇
ROBINSON: Whoa, whoa, whoa!
发动机出毛病了
There's something wrong with the motor.
收音机里的人：他来了……他慢下来了
MAN ON RADIO: He's coming to a...he's slowing down.
下面一切都好吗
Everything okay down there?
收音机里的人：看起来不错
MAN ON RADIO: Seems okay.
罗宾逊：真的很强劲
ROBINSON: It is going really strong,
是的  哇  哇  哇
and it's, whoa, whoa, whoa.
男士：请假
MAN: Main off?
罗宾逊：是的  男：好的
ROBINSON: Yeah. MAN: Okay.
罗宾逊：大约每小时378英里左右
ROBINSON: Got up to right around 378 miles an hour,
然后涡轮车钩脱落了
and then the turbo coupler came off.
真令人沮丧
It's frustrating.
这是一个巨大的团队努力
It's a huge team effort,
而且  你知道  我们都在努力实现我们的目标
and, you know, we're all trying to reach our goal.
大概95%的时间有问题
Probably 95% of the time there is something going wrong.
这就是为什么记录能持续这么久的原因
That's why records last so long.
关于陆地速度赛车的一切
Everything about land speed racing
学习新事物和改进方法
is learning what's new and how to improve things.
我们学到了很多  我想我们可以好好利用它
We learn a lot, and I think we can put that to good use
未来
in the future.
史密斯：这件事我和洛基在一起
SMITH: I'm with Rocky on this.
你被击倒了  你又回来了
You get knocked down, you get back up again.
沟通有助于你面对失败而不畏惧
Communicating helps you face failure without fear.
但是我们的大脑会适应
But our brains adapt.
所以如果我们失去沟通的能力
So if we lose the ability to communicate,
我们的大脑可能会找到办法
our brain might find a work-around.
它很灵活
It's flexible.
和利兰谈谈就知道了
Talk to Leland about it.
梅尔文：在康复期间
MELVIN: During the time of recovery
从我的听力事故中
from my hearing accident,
有一点我能感觉到我的大脑在重新布线
there was a point when I could feel my brain rewiring itself
再听一遍
to hear again.
随着时间的推移  大脑可以做出调整
The brain over time can make adjustments
赔偿损失或变化
to compensate for losses or changes.
我想这就是发生在我身上的事
And I think that's what happened to me.
我的听力开始恢复
My hearing started coming back
事故发生三周后
about three weeks after my accident.
但我又花了两年时间才恢复正常
But it took two more years for me to recover properly.
最后  NASA首席医疗官
Then finally, the chief medical officer for NASA
拿出一张纸
pulled out a piece of paper
这就是说    你现在可以在太空飞行了
that said, 'You are now cleared to fly in space.'
那是我一生中最不可思议的日子之一
That was one of the most incredible days of my life.
我再也不认为我的大脑是理所当然的了
I never took my brain for granted again.
史密斯：有了灵活的大脑
SMITH: With that flexible brain,
我们学习  适应和解决问题
we learn, adapt, and problem solve.
我们的大脑给我们语言
Our brains give us language,
让我们与他人分享这些教训
allowing us to share those lessons with others.
写作让我们通过时间传递知识
And writing lets us pass on that knowledge through time.
林格：所有的人类脑力
LINENGER: All that human brain power,
所有的知识都通过书面教科书
all that knowledge through written textbooks,
通过计算  通过数学
through calculations, through mathematics.
霍夫曼：那导致了一场大爆炸
HOFFMAN: That just led to a huge explosion
在文明的发展中
in the development of civilization.
惠特森：我们可以变得更聪明
WHITSON: We can get a lot smarter,
因为我们可以从上一代学到更多
because we can learn a lot more from the previous generations.
史密斯：人类是通过思想网络联系在一起的
SMITH: Humanity is linked together by a network of minds
跨越时间和空间
that spans time and space.
这帮助我们创造了令人眼花缭乱的复杂性
And that's helped us create things of dazzling complexity.
我们所做的最复杂的事情就是漂浮在我们的上方
The most complex one we've ever made is floating above us.
收音机上的人：点火顺序开始
MAN ON RADIO: Ignition sequence start.
五  四  三  二  一
Five, four, three, two, one.
梅尔文：你要离开这个星球
MELVIN: You're lifting off of the planet.
感觉胸部有3个重力
Feeling 3 Gs on your chest
当你被推进宇宙的时候
as you're being propelled to the cosmos.
这真是一次了不起的旅行
It is one heck of a ride.
梅尔文：失去听觉后
MELVIN: After losing the sense of hearing,
我花了很多年才到达发射台
it took so many years for me to get to the launchpad,
但仅仅几分钟就到达了轨道
but it just took a few minutes to get to orbit.
广播员：早上好  休斯顿
MAN ON RADIO: Good morning, Houston.
梅尔文：我们到了太空  我看到了这个星球
MELVIN: We got to space, I saw the planet.
它只会打动你的头脑
It just blows your mind.
这一抹色彩
This burst of color.
我从未见过如此鲜艳的色彩
I've never seen colors that vibrant before.
我几乎必须  像  拍打自己才能回去工作
And I almost had to, like, smack myself to get back to work.
收音机里的人：如果你能找到另一个…
MAN ON RADIO: If you could get the other...
探险队的四名队员  我们已经看到他们了
the expedition four crew, that we have them in sight.
梅尔文：然后我看到地平线上有一个小点
MELVIN: And then I saw this little dot out on the horizon.
我们越来越近了
And we get closer and closer and closer.
我第一次看到空间站在上空飞行
The first time I saw the space station flying overhead,
我不知道这个飞船有多复杂
I never knew how complex a vehicle it was.
你知道  你可以看到复杂的设计
You know, you could see the intricate design
在这些模块中  所有这些东西
in these modules, all these things
这是人脑想象出来的
that were envisioned by the human brain.
惠特森：所以  你知道  当你接近它的时候
WHITSON: So, you know, when you approach it,
真是太美了
it's just so beautiful.
这是一个令人惊叹的工程奇迹
It's an amazing, amazing engineering marvel.
霍夫曼：毫无疑问  太空站
HOFFMAN: There's no question that the space station
是最伟大的国际科学项目
is the greatest international scientific project
这是有史以来的
that's ever been undertaken.
林格：就像  哇  这东西太棒了
LINENGER: It's like, wow, this thing is awesome.
我要靠这东西
And I'm gonna get to live on that thing
生活四五个月
for four or five months.
收音机里的人：现在拿着相机进来了
MAN ON RADIO: Coming in now and carrying the camera,
任务专家Leland Melvin
mission specialist Leland Melvin.
男：你好吗
MAN: How you doing?
老兄 ”公牛闯进了瓷器店“
MAN: Bull in a china shop, man.
梅尔文：爬”这座山“到太空
MELVIN: Climbing this hill to space
是我做过的最难的事情之一
was one of the hardest things I've ever done.
我从没想过自己会聋
I never imagined myself going deaf,
我从没想过会回来
I never imagined coming back
在那次事故之后得到这个机会
and getting this opportunity after that accident.
这对所有人类来说都是一个类似的故事
And it's really a similar story for all of humankind.
我们作为一个物种所取得的一切
Everything we've achieved as a species
是一系列幸运事故的产物
is the product of a lucky chain of accidents.
史密斯：要到这里  我们需要一颗行星从尘埃中凝结出来
SMITH: To get here, we needed a planet to congeal out of dust.
在生命形成和塑造我们世界的正确地方
In the right place for life to form and mold our world,
让我们呼吸并变得复杂
allowing us to breathe and grow complex.
我们需要避开太阳
We needed to be shielded from our sun,
有月亮的恩赐
gifted with a moon,
以及季节的授予
and granted seasons.
我们只需要足够的轰炸
We needed just enough bombardments
几乎湮灭
and near-annihilations
让生命漫步
to let life meander
通过它的曲折
through its twists and turns
进化出一个物种
and evolve a species
像你我一样复杂的大脑
with a brain as complex as yours and mine.
梅尔文：我在空间站的时候
MELVIN: When I was on the space station,
回首地球
looking back at the planet,
我对它抱着深刻的谢意
it gave me a profound appreciation
在我们认为理所当然的事情上
in what we take for granted.
人类是一个奇妙的  非凡的怪人
Humans are a wonderful, extraordinary oddity.
史密斯：干得好  伙计  很棒的游戏
SMITH: Good job, man, great game.
有了这个果冻
With this blob of Jell-O,
860亿神经元
these 86 billion neurons,
我们可以离开这个星球
we've left the planet
远眺宇宙
and looked far, far out into the universe,
试图揭开宇宙的奥秘
trying to unravel the mysteries of the cosmos.
但不管我们看地有多遥远
But no matter how far out we look,
我们发现的最遥远的东西
the most far-out thing we've ever found
就在我们耳边
is right between our ears.
下一次
Next time...
当你最终回到地球时  感觉如何
What does it feel like when you finally come back to Earth?
真的没有像家这样的地方吗
Is there really no place like home?